A Guide to the James Russell Boldridge papers, 1869-1978
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
James Russell Boldridge papers, 1869-1978
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
1985/Apr/7
1.79 linear feet.
Boldridge, James Russell, 1885-1983
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
A gift from Edward Barbour Boldridge of Rixeyville, VA donated in 1985.
Biographical Information
Dr. James Russell Boldridge (1885-1983) was born at Brown's Store in Culpeper County, Virginia to Dr. James Barbour Boldridge and Laura Henry Boldridge. He graduated from the Medical College of Virginia in 1909 and then served an internship at Retreat for the Sick Hospital. He began a general practice in 1910 covering parts of Culpeper, Rappahannock, and Fauquier Counties. At the time he began his practice there were four doctors in the town of Culpeper and eight more in the county. Though it was a rural area the poor road conditions made it necessary to have a doctor in each community. During World War I he served on the draft board for Culpeper County. Boldridge continued to practice until he was 90 years old.
Boldridge married Annie Marie Hess, a registered nurse, in 1912. They had four sons James Russell Jr., William Franklin, Edward Barbour, and John Henry. In addition to his medical practice Boldridge owned "Homeland," a 344 acre farm located in Rixeyville, Virginia which he purchased in 1918. Boldridge died in 1983 at the age of 97.
Scope and Content
The papers of Dr. James Russell Boldridge pertain mostly to his time in medical school and in medical practice. The collection also includes some personal papers. Types of materials include case notes, certificates and diplomas, clippings, correspondence, day books and diaries, financial records, legal records, letcure notes, photographs, and other related materials. The materials related to his medical practice provide insight into the work of the rural medical practitioner especially during the years just prior to World War I.
Series 1: Professional papers, 1908-1978. This series is composed of materials related to Boldridge's work as a physician. Items include account books for his practice, certficates and diplomas, correspondence, which includes exchanges with other doctors regarding his patients' cases, case notes, a day book and diaries with brief notes on patient visits, legal records, opium distribution license and order forms, and records of birth.
Series 2: Medical school papers, 1905-1909. This series includes materials from Boldridge's time as a student at the Medical College of Virginia. These materials include case studies, exams, lectures notes prepared by his instructors on dermatology, surgery, and tumors, his own notes including a notebook with prescription preparations, and copies of the Virginia State Board of Medical Examiners exams.
Series 3: Personal papers, 1869-1872, 1899-1960. This series contains some personal materials which include correspondence, clippings, a ledger, photographs, the records from his administration of the Robert L. Browning estate of which he was the executor, and other miscellaneous items.
Arrangement
These papers are divided into 3 series: Series 1: Professional papers, 1908-1978; Series 2: Medical school papers, 1905-1909; and Series 3: Personal papers, 1869-1960.
Efforts have been made to maintain the origial organization where applicable. The files are arranged alphabetically within each series and materials within the files are arranged chronologically where applicable.
Index Terms
Persons:
Boldridge, James Russell, 1885-1983
Corporate Names:
Medical College of Virginia; Virginia Commonwealth University
Subjects:
Medicine, Rural--History--20th century--Virginia.
Geographical Names:
Culpeper County (Va.); Rappahannock County (Va.)
Contents List
- Professional papers, 1908-1978 (Box 1-2)
  - Account books, 1910-1912, 1918-1921, Two oversize volumes (Box 2)
  - Certificates, diplomas, & licenses, 1909-1978 (Box-folder 1:1 & 2:1 (oversize))
  - Correspondence, 1908-1959 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Case notes & misc., undated, 1925, 1937 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Day book, 1916-1918 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Diaries, 1926, 1939 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Legal records, 1913-1914, 1935 (Box-folder 1:6)
    Primarily warrants in debt taken out by Boldridge for outstanding debts owed by patients.
  - Opium order form & license to disperse, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Physician's record of a birth, 1914-196, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Receipts, 1926-1928, 1940 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Medical school papers, 1905-1909 (Box 1)
  - Case studies (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Exams, 1905-1909 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Lecture notes: dermatology, lecturer Dr. F. H. Beadles, 1905-1909 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Lecture notes: practice of surgery (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Lecture notes: surgery (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Lecture notes: tumors, lecturer Dr. J. Shelton Horsley (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Notes (Box-folder 1:16)
    Miscellaneous course notes and one notebook with prescription preparations.
  - Virginia State Board of Medical Examiners, exams 1905, 1909 (Box-folder 1:17)
- Personal papers 1869-1960 (Box 1-2)
  - Clippings, 1927, 1937, 1953-1959 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Correspondence, 1899, 1918, 1923, 1938, 1953-1960 (Box-folder 1:19)
    Includes a letter and newspaper clipping from Thomas Summers regarding the death of his son, Dr. Bronson Ewing Summers duing the 1918 influenza epidemic. Dr. Summers, a 1912 MCV graduate, was a surgeon in the U.S. Marine Corps and became ill while working at the base hospital in Quantico, Virginia.
  - Ledger, 1869-1872, One oversize volume (Box 2)
    A ledger with accounts for general merchandise, timber, shingles, and various individuals in Rappahannock County, Virginia. The owner(s) of the ledger are unknown. It is possible that it belonged to James Madison Wood and/or Samuel J. Spindle based on an enclosed bill, but there is not enough information to verify it for certain.
  - Photographs & images, undated, 1959 (Box-folder 1:20 & 2:1 (oversize))
  - Play bill, 1935 (Box-folder 1:21)
    "Meet Uncle Sally," presented by the senior class of Washington High School, Rappahannock County, Virginia.
  - Robert L. Browning estate, 1913, 1915, 1935-1940 (Box-folder 1:22-23)
  - Seed and water test results, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 1:24)